# 哈喽大家好
Hello everyone
# 这个猪肉我们本来是想等让他价格下去一点再做这个腊肉
Speaking of pork, we planned to wait for a price drop to make some larou (Chinese cured pork)
# 看来等不了了
It appears that we can't wait
# 我四伯爷说
Uncle said
# 可能会越等越高所以就买看半头猪
the price can be even higher as we wait, so we just bought half a pig
# 跟去年一样也是做半头100多斤一点
Same as the last year, it weighs a bit more than 100 jin (jin = 500g)
# 开始吧
Let's get started
# 我来试一下这个跟腿有好重哦
Let me see how heavy this leg is
# 几十斤嘛
A few dozens of jin
# 拿得起不哦 起码有40多斤嘛
Can you lift it? It's at least 40 jin
# 50斤都有害怕
Or even 50 I'm afraid
# 50斤都有
Yeah, 50 jin
# 等会儿那个前腿留下来我改天做个肘子
You can leave the front leg for me. I can make a knuckle dish some day
# 哪里做肘子用前腿做哦
Who in the world uses front legs for knuckles?
# 前肘都嘛
Front knuckle, you know
# 前肘肉多点
A front knuckle has more meat
# 你帮斗他整
Could you help him?
# 你帮斗四伯爷整 我整不归一
Could you help uncle? I can't do it well
# 哪里有弄不归一的哦
There's nothing as "can't do it well"
# 眼见之功的活路
???
# 我没得你弄得好都嘛
I mean, I can't do it as well as you
# 那还用说
Any questions for that?
# 看你搞得拿行我摸到手都是爪的
???
# 是啊
Yeah
# 看哪天（小）二娃回来我喊他叫我耍微信了
When my son is back, I'll ask him to teach me WeChat # 小二娃是四伯的儿子，出镜较少，不是漆二娃
# 人家全都耍微信老子耍不归一
Everyone is now using WeChat, but I don't know how
# 我都可以教你撒
I can also teach you
# 你要把你的老人机换了
You need to switch your dumb phone first
# 哦噢
Oh
# 这个时候做腊肉还没迟撒
It's not too late to make larou, is it?
# 不得迟
It's not
# 排骨咋子砍法哦
How to chop the ribs?
# 诶 剔了来
Eh, you need to divide it first
# 把排骨抬了来（剔排骨）
Divide the ribs from the pig
# 四伯爷来 四伯爷专业点
Let uncle do it. Uncle is more professional
# 你得后面打哈下手就是
You can stay back and help
# 我等会儿剔下来你划肉可以
I'll divide it first, then you can slice it
# 我都只有在旁边望斗
Like you, I can only stay here watching
# 挨都挨不拢（插不上手）
Can't get involved
# 可以
Alright
# 好要得了 你去划那个 我来剔排骨
Good, you can slice it now. I'll divide the ribs
# 还要得
Good
# 哪里要得了这么厚哦
Not good, it's too thick
# 这些瘦肉要取下来
Have to cut off the lean meat first
# 太厚了
It's too thick
# 看你划窄点还是划宽点
Do you want to make thinner or thicker slices?
# 划窄点就要连着划两刀
You need to slice twice at the same position for thinner slices
# 这样子再划一刀嘛
Slice again here
# 看起来安逸点
Looks nice
# 厚了还腌不透
Hard to cure if it's too thick
# 切小坨点
Let's make smaller pieces
# 去年是100几呢 130多斤噶
How much was it last year? Over 100 jin? 130 jin?
# 去年还要重点
It was heavier last year
# 去年子钱还相因 相因好多
Last year the price was cheaper. Cheaper by a lot
# 便宜了差不多一半
Cheaper by almost half
# 这是你们的鸡吗 四伯爷
Are these your chickens, uncle?
# 嗯
Yes
# 老母鸡
Old hens
# 我四伯以前卖猪的时候他这个
Before, when uncle selled a pig
# 卖一头猪挣点钱
He selled a pig and earned some money
# 然后剩下的猪就当时赚的
And the leftover pork was counted as bonus
# 现在这个猪肉涨得厉害
Now the pork price is rising hard
# 一头猪平时卖不了有时候半头都卖不了
It's hard to sell a whole pig, or even half sometimes
# 卖不了怎么办呢
What can we do then?
# 工钱搭进去了不说剩的肉还要自己倒贴钱
We can't earn the money, and even have to pay for the leftover meat
# 是不哦
Is that right?
# 嗯
Yeah
# 这块排骨可以
The ribs are good
# 这个鸡真的要吃肉诶
Eh, the chicken can eat meat for real
# 捡点肉渣渣给它吃
Feed it with some meat scrap
# 这个肉直接丢得盆子里哦
Just drop the meat in the basin?
# 可以啊
Yeah
# 你来丢嘛漆二娃 我去炒盐巴去了
Come do it, Qi Erwa. I'll roast the salt
# 100多斤肉放2-3斤（盐）
For about 100 jin of pork, we need 2-3 jin (of salt)
# 这一包是2斤
This pack weighs 2 jin
# 放一包半 3斤盐
We'll use 1 pack and a half, which is 3 jin
# 大概一包半的样子
About 1 pack and a half
# 放点香料
Put some spices
# 做腊肉嘛少不了花椒
We can't miss Sichuan peppercorns for larou
# 四川人吃花椒都是一把一把的
We Sichuanese eat tons of Sichuan peppercorns
# 去年我们也做了100多斤的腊肉
Last year, we also made over 100 jin of larou
# 其实这个腊肉跟香肠吧就是说
Actually, speaking of larou and sausages
# 在家里面把这个肉做好了
You can make it at home
# 给外面的亲戚呀朋友呀带一点
and bring it to your friends and relatives
# 行
Good
# 炒香了已经
Aromatic now
# 狗儿咯
Dog! (Come here)
# 不用刀了嘎
We don't need knives now?
# 刀应该不用了
We shouldn't
# 这里有好多点哦
How much is there?
# 差不多3两酒
Roughly 3 liang of baijiu liquor (liang = 50g)
# 3两酒差不多
3 liang of baijiu, yeah
# 够不够哦
Is it enough?
# 这点到够等会儿整排骨又重新搞
???
# 酒不关事酒可以多整点儿
Baijiu doesn't matter. We can put more
# 这个酒多放点越多越香
The more baijiu, the better it tastes
# 要把它打湿把这个肉
Gotta moisture the pork
# 你还有么有冰糖嘛
Do you have white rock sugar?
# 我们做这个腊肉香不香就看这个酒度数高不高
Whether the larou is flavorful fully depends on how strong the baijiu liquor is
# 酒香不香
and whether it is flavorful
# 敲烂把冰糖敲烂
Crush it (the rock sugar)
# 这个酒是不是少了嘛
Is there too little baijiu?
# 不得少
Not too little
# 没打湿均匀都嘛
It isn't moistured evenly, is it?
# 不得少
Not too little
# 放不完
Can't use it up
# 肯定放不完撒
Can't use it up for use
# 放一半
Add half of it
# 烫不烫哦
Is it hot?
# 就是有点烫
It's a little hot
# 烫就这样撒
Do it like this if it's hot
# 你还拿手抓
And you used your bare hands
# 清不到
???
# 我清得到都嘛拿在手里那个重量
# 好好好好了
Okay 'kay 'kay, okay
# 好了
Oh-Kay
# 你说好就好
It's okay if you said so
# 整咸了
So salty
# 越放越咸
It get even more salty after curing
# 吃咸点看淡点就是
???
# 噶 四伯爷
Right, uncle?
# 这个要放一点老姜放下去那个味道更好
(In Standard Chinese) Put some old ginger, so it tastes better
# 你的普通话还是椒盐味的哦
Your Putonghua (Standard Chinese) is "salt-and-pepper" accented!
# 我的普通话好差啊
Is my Putonghua bad?
# 白话（粤语）都不在话下
Even "Baihua" (Cantonese) is easy piecy
# 叫粤语
That's called Cantonese
# 这下子把排骨直接丢进去
Dump the ribs in directly
# 抓2把盐巴都够了
Two handful of salt should be enough
# 少抓点二娃这个少抓点
Not too much, don't put too much # 不知道这里的二娃是哪个二娃...
# 这里面有盐水都嘛 化了就要下流下去
There's salt water inside. It gets dissolved and flows down
# 上面的盐水化下去就可以了
Just let the salt water flow down. That's enough
# 好 拿去盖起来
Alright, close it
# 你的意思是排骨放下面肉放上面哦
Do you mean, the ribs at the bottom, and the meat on the top
# 哦 对
Oh, yeah
# 好搞定
Alright, done
# 排归一撒 你那乱七八糟的丢
Can you put it nicely? You are messing around
# 排骨没加冰糖的
We haven't added rock sugar to the ribs
# 肉上面有冰糖都嘛
The meat has rock sugar, right?
# 这都有冰糖的 还要翻的都嘛
It already has rock sugar. And we need to flip it
# 排归一你那乱七八糟的丢起看到都不顺眼
Put it nicely. It's too messy, looks bad
# 好重哦
It's so heavy
# 100哒100斤肉
100 jin of pork
# 2000多块钱
More than 2,000 yuan